Miguel Rivera-Lanas

Data scientist/engineer with 4 years experience in investment management. Interested in research roles focusing on ML/AI bias and computational social science. Primarily focused on empirical methods to study quantitative and social effects of disinformation propagation and content moderation systems.

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist / Engineer — **Point72**, NYC, NY September 2019 - Present

- Sept 2019 to Aug. 2020, I was part of a research group, investigating novel data sets, including credit-card transaction data and others, for evaluating trends and statistical relationships to company fundamental KPIs.
- In Sept. 2020, I joined an investment team with 8 sector analysts, where I manage all data science and engineering projects.
- Implement statistical descriptive modeling, preprocessing, feature engineering, and forecasting over a diverse range of data sets related to oil well production, retail consumer trends, and other sectors.
- Build systematic strategy backtesting and risk analysis frameworks
- Build scalable and robust cloud based event-driven ETL architecture for delivering continuous reporting of data products

Research Associate, Fixed Income — AllianceBernstein, NYC, NY June 2016 - August 2016, June 2017 - August 2019

- Rotations as research associate for macro economics, quantitative research, and portfolio strategy technology teams
- Developed and maintained ETL, preprocessing, and reporting for novel liquidity signals from live order-book data, utilized by traders to better assess supply and demand conditions for specific parts of the market.

VOLUNTEERING

Volunteer Developer — Statisticians without Borders (SWB) November 2020 - March 2021

- Worked as a data engineer over 15 weeks as part of a SWB volunteer team on behalf of the Indian non-profit, India Excellence Forum (IEF)
- Our team achieved our objective to develop a web dashboard for evaluating COVID-19 related epidemiological model results to assist municipal health organizations in India.

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA — B.A., Cum Laude August 2013 - May 2017

Major: Economics, Minors(s): Statistics, International Relations

Clubs:

- Check One: Board Member. Student organization providing a discussion space for personal and societal experiences involving race and mixed-heritage backgrounds.
- Penn Journal of Economics: Editorial Committee. (PJE) is a semi-annual, peer-reviewed publication of honors theses and other academic projects for undergraduates and faculty.

Email:

miguelriveralanas@gmail.com

Github: rivera-lanasm **Website:** rivera-lanasm.com

CORE COMPETENCIES

Scripting: Python, Scala, R

Development: Git, Airflow, Docker **Cloud:** AWS (S3, EC2, RDS, Lambda,

SNS, Glue Jobs)

Databases: PostgresSQL, MongoDB **ML:** Sklearn, Tensorflow, SpaCy **Data Manipulation:** Pandas, Numpy, SciPy, BeautifulSoup, Spark, Tidyverse

Web Dashboard: Plotly Dash

INTERESTS

Computational Social Science, Misinformation, Fairness and Bias in ML/AI

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Visit www.rivera-lanasm.com/post/

- Logic/Probability Puzzles:
- Logic and math puzzles solved with analytical and probabilistic methods. Solutions coded primarily in **Scala**.

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent), Spanish (Fluent), French (Working Proficiency)